excellent and we're away okay so welcome
everybody to the first episode of active
inference insights brought to you by the
active inference Institute I am your
host darus parvey Wayne and today I have
the privilege of speaking to Professor
Carl friston one of the most
revolutionary thinkers in the fields of
Neuroscience cognitive science
theoretical biology and dare I say
physics and philosophy a leading
Authority in neuroimaging he is the
inventor of statistical parametric
modeling and voxal based morry I hope I
pronounce that correctly more recently
he has posited the free energy principle
which is technically a normative account
of self-organization in terms of optimal
Basi and design or in other words a
description of how things continue to be
things as such his groundbreaking ideas
hold profound implications not only for
biology and psychology but also the the
very nature of reality itself ladies and
gentlemen it is my honor to introduce
Professor K friston Professor friston
thank you so much for joining us well
thank you thank you for that lovely
introduction what you can say is I I
just invented lots of three-letter
acronyms that's much
simpler so you have and I sense a lot of
freeletter acronyms have also spawned
from from a lot of your
work um excellent well this podcast this
is the first episode so as I was saying
sort of off camera this is very exciting
for me hopefully very exciting for
everyone tuning in the kind of uh the
reason why it's come about is that we
wanted the active inference Institute
wanted a way to introduce the ideas of
active inference and the free energy
principle perhaps to an audience who
were not PhD holders scholars in the
area but had a kind of latent interest
in Psychology Neuroscience maths biology
whatever it is and wanted to explore
these ideas a little bit fter a little
bit further so it's a non specialized
introduction to the ideas of active
inference and the free energy principle
and as the author inventor discoverer of
the free energy principle we can have an
interesting philosophical conversation
about what that is um it's it's an
absolute Delight to have you so I guess
my first question that I need to ask for
everyone listening is could you give us
a very brief or not very brief but a
very um accessible definition of the
free energy
principle um what free energy is and how
you know what this what this principle
says about reality and
ourselves yes I'm not very good at
giving brief answers but do my we have
we have a while so so go
ahead um so just to put things in
context um the free energy principle is
a principle um as read by a physicist or
engineer that means it's a method um
much like Hamilton's principle of least
action that you can apply um so one
might ask what are the S the most
important applications of the free
energy principle I guess that would be
active inference so I will answer your
question and I will say what the free
energy principle is but um that may have
to be qualified by looking specifically
at the application which is active
inflence and what that means um
theologically her istically you know
what it brings to the table when you do
apply the free energy principle but the
free energy principle itself um is just
a description of things that persist or
exist and it rests upon a careful
specification of what you mean by a
thing um it starts with the exactly the
same assumptions that all of physics
starts with basically a random dynamical
system some people describe that in
terms of um stochastic differential
equations for if you're not familiar
with that kind of description is just
saying that you can describe the
universe in terms of the way that states
change as a function of themselves so
it's a very generic um description of
Any Given universe that just commits to
the notion that there is a state of the
universe and it could be very high
dimensional and that it has some
Dynamics so that's where the free energy
principle starts but the special thing
about the free energy principle um that
distinguishes it from other um
formulations in physics for example
Quantum thermodynamics um statistical
and classical mechanics all of which can
be if you like derived from this basic
description of the world as a random
dynamical system the thing that um
separates the free energy principle uh
or gives it its particular flavor is a
careful distinction between the states
of something and everything else uh and
the way that we do that is by inducing a
separation you know uh technically a
partition of all possible States into
three kinds the states of something that
are internal to the thing everything
else external to the thing and then
crucially a set of states that separate
seate the uh internal from the external
states that allow and couple the inside
to the outside and that's referred to as
a um the blanket States or a Markoff
blanket or boundary um so a lot of this
rests upon this this notion of a
boundary that um on the one hand
separates the inside from the outside of
something and by a thing I mean anything
from a small particle to a to a priest
or a person anything that can can be
individuated and uh possesses
characteristic States constitutes
something um and with tongue and cheek
you therefore have a theory of every
space thing not everything but every
thing
um so this Mark of boundary or Mark of
blanket um um is a sort of crucial
device um in the sense that it allows
you to individuate something from
everything else but at the same time it
um couples the internal to the external
States so we're now talking about a
special kind of physics and probably a
more ubiquitous kind of physics which is
the physics of open systems um because
the inside is now vicariously open to in
exchange with the outside across the
Markoff blanket and just um for interest
because this will be relevant later on
for active inference we usually divide
the
uh blanket States into active and
sensory states that can be regarded very
simply as of the inputs and the outputs
um uh technically the um the inputs of
the sensory states are defined in um in
the sense that the in internal states
don't influence the sensory States and
conversely the active states are defined
such that the external states don't
influence the the active States so but
more simply what we're saying is that
something can be defined in terms of the
influences upon it and the influences
that it exerts through the blanket
states on the outside world so just
given that assumption um that
entails um existence in the sense that
to Define this Markoff blanket you have
to um you need for the system to have
some characteristic States technically
an attracting set of states that you'd
find the thing in just by assuming the
existence of this attracting set of this
random dynamical system that possesses
this distinction between the inside and
the outside everything else follows and
everything else simply put is you can
read the internal and active States
sometimes refer to as the autonomous
states of a particle or a priest or a
person um as
um either if you're a phys IST
conforming to a particular principle of
least action and that principle of least
action is that um it minimizes the path
integral of the variation of free energy
um if you want to think of this more
intuitively because that free energy
also stands in for or is an
approximation to a bound upon model
evidence you can also say that it must
be the case that the autonomous states
of anything
will look as if they are trying to
maximize the evidence for what we would
now um consider the internal states to
be um a model of what's going on on the
outside so um some people refer to that
as self- evidencing um so if I just
repeat that from the physicist point of
view given the the assumption that
you've got this random dynamical system
with an attracting set that can that has
this partition that allows you to
individuate something within this system
it has to be the case that the Dynamics
of the autonomous states of that system
um perform a gradient flow on a quantity
called variation free
energy that's it is that interesting
well it becomes interesting if you
realize that this variation free energy
has a particular meaning and a you um a
particular interpretation that gives you
a teleology for this kind of dynamic uh
and that Tey is often referred to in
terms of basy mechanics why well because
the um the free energy the variational
free energy is the same quantity that
measures the evidence for a generative
model of the causes of some data if
you're a
statistician and in this instance the
data that we're talking about are the
impressions of the outside State on the
on the Markoff blanket so um what you're
now in a position or you now in a
position you are now licensed to talk
about anything that exists in some
simple Elemental sense uh performing
inference and possessing this or
evincing this kind of basing mechanics
um and in philosophy um people like
yakob har nice summarizes as self-
evidencing so you can imagine that it
looks as if anything that exists is
basically moving in a way uh sensing and
acting upon its World in a way that's
Garing um evidence for its own existence
so it's this is you know if you like a
slight cheat in the sense that you what
we're doing is describing the Dynamics
of something that exists and then we're
saying ah but it now looks as if
it in in in virtue of its existence it
is now it can be described theologically
as acting to gather evidence for its own
existence its own um um its own
structure and that structure entails a
generative model of what's going on on
the outside so how does that help
well it doesn't really help in any
fundamental way other than it's very
pretty and it it's it's nice to talk
about basy mechanics as being a sort of
complement uh or another kind of physics
that comes from the same stable as
quantum mechanics and cystic mechanics
and I repeat classical or lran mechanics
um however there is a nice um
application at hand once you realize
that this uh once you interpret um the
variation free energy in terms of a um
technically the logarithm of some model
evidence what that means is that you can
now build things you can build things
and you can simulate those things why
well because you know that their
Dynamics must be um conforming to this
principle of least action um uh another
way of thinking about this is that it um
does a gradi in descent or hill climbing
on a particular um functional which is
um this um variation free energy or the
negative variation free energy which is
the log evidence so um because this log
evidence uh is a function of a model
that just is a description of the
characteristic States things occupy or
things are found in um you can now write
down the generative model which is just
a probability distribution over the
characteristic States or defining the
characteristic States you want your
thing to be attracted to this is the
attracting set and once you've written
down your generative model you can then
work out the gradients um of the free
energy functional of that generative
model and then you can simply um
integrate or mathematically solve for
the Dynamics the flow the motion the
movement of this thing so I know this
isn't terribly accessible but it's it's
uh uh a way I think of these things that
you are
uh now in a position instead of just
looking at something and saying oh I
wonder what uh generative model um would
be fit for purpose to describe this
particular thing you can now turn that
on its head and say okay I want this
kind of thing and I'm going to describe
and Define this kind of thing with a
particular gened model I just have to
write down the probability distribution
um over the causes and consequences from
the point of view of the thing in
question namely the external States and
its Impressions upon um the Markoff
blanket and once I've written that down
I can now simulate the autonomous States
I can now create a little autonomous
artifact a little autonomous particle
that behaves in exactly the same way as
something that existed that had that
kind of generative model so it's a very
practical if you like um uh it's a
principle that can be applied in a very
practical way to simulate things and if
you can then simulate at things you can
start to build things you can start to
um
um do computational Neuroscience you can
start to sort of naturalize cognitive um
neuroscience and possibly even sort of
um psychology in terms of the physics
that is inherent in this basing
mechanics that comes from the free
energy principle um you can also start
to ask questions about the beliefs of
another person why well part of this
generative model or
um the generative model can always be
sort of um split into two things sort of
priors before you see some data and the
likelihood the likelihood of that data
given um the causes of that data these
will be the external States so you have
pry belief over the causes the external
States and you have a likelihood that
Maps the causes to the consequences
which are your observations so your
Sensations um and therefore you can now
fiddle with and say um a synthetic
subject or person who is being simulated
in the computer until their behavior
their actions possibly their decisions
matches that of Any Given um cohort or
any given um um subject or animal um and
then having adjusted the prior part of
the generative model and possibly the
likelihood you've now basically created
a digital
twin that emulates the same kind of
belief updating the same kind of basing
mechanics um that you can now infer as
possessed by the thing in question so
this is a um sort of quite a high-end
application which which is um you know
one of the the um the motivations for um
de for developing the free energy
principle and and active influences an
application um that it enables you to
essentially phenotype another thing
another person for example in terms of
this belief updating in terms of this
basing mechanics um and that can be
quite useful in context when you want to
understand how people work and
particularly how their belief updating
works this becomes particularly
interesting in the context of
computational
Psychiatry where you want to be able to
explain people's behavior in terms of
what do they Bel about the world out
there you know how how um how are they
sense making how are they assimilating
evidence for their world model which you
can read as the generative model U and
under what priors are they doing doing
this sort of basian um assimilation or
evidence accumulation um the underwrites
their decisions so that's one um um one
particular application there be other
applications um you know if you want to
make intelligent artifacts or you want
to understand the mechanisms of belief
updating at different temporal scales um
belief sharing between two things that
are in communication or transacting
across the a shared markof blanket or
indeed uh looking at a shared World um
and then one can start to get into the
world of um distributed cognition and
Federated inference there are all sorts
of things you can do once you start to
apply active
inference yeah that was that was
fantastic I mean we have a lot to get
our get our teeth into um and and
probably some Concepts there that are
new to a to to our audience so it might
be worth sort of backtracking certain
things and and and trying
to um find a kind of yeah a
let's sort of dissect some of these
Concepts together um the first thing I
want to speak about is this notion that
the internal States in some sense
embody um the kind of desirable model
given their attractor State the
desirable model of the world I think um
one of these one of the questions that
one has when one enters into the world
of active inference is whether an
organism is a model or whether an
organism has model and here we sort of
have a a backtrack to cybernetics and
the good regulator theorem that all good
um regulatory systems have a model of
their environment if we think about
thermostats or um anything alike so
maybe it's worth un unpacking that
because I think a lot of people might
have this intuitive sense that there's a
homunculus in the brain which has a
model of the world and it's very
internalist but maybe from a more
physics perspective we can adopt a more
externalist position position where
there isn't this little thing which has
a sort of Representative picture of the
world but actually is just
enacting um some model of itself which
in many ways is just some it some
version of the of its external Dynamics
um so let's start there because I think
that will feed nicely into maybe a
conversation about internal and external
Dynamics and exactly what that looks
like in the free energy
principle yeah that that's a great
question and uh you some sort of deep
issues Unearthed by that and it's nice
you've introduced cybernetics and notion
of the good regulator theorem because
you know in one on one view I think you
could look at um the free energy
Principle as just a 21st century version
of that kind of cytic thinking there are
other there are other things that the
free energy principal inherits uh from
um you know James's Max men principle
lots of ideas in in in Psychology
perceptions hypothesis testing there are
lots of different um roads that converge
upon this um um formulation um that that
is uner in terms of the free energy
principle um but that particular
question is is really interesting uh I
have to say that I usually um try to
elude that question by saying that the
the internal States entail a generative
model so um however I um if I had if one
was pressed upon it um then
um I would say very clearly uh that the
internal States um the thing is a
generative model it's not if you like um
a picture that you painted in terms of
that hunus looking at its sort of you
know its virtual reality inside its head
and trying to what's going on it is
instantiated it is realized in its
physics in its existence in its Dynamics
um the reason I use the word entailed is
that the generative model um is um
technically uh just a probability
distribution um so you you ask yourself
well does a probability distribution
exist um in some physical sense um and
the answer is well no um a probability
distribution is what it is it's a a
mathematical description um however that
um probability distribution will have
sufficient
statistics that could exist
so what I'm saying is that um for
example let's take a ging distribution
um you know I can I can um Express
mathematically I can write down the
notation for your ging a bell-shaped
distribution over some variable that
goes from plus to minus infinity um or I
can say I can
characterize or specify this ging
distribution in terms of its mean and
its variance and and those are two
numbers that are not random variables
they are sufficient statistics and it
may be and in fact it is the case that
that the um the free energy principle
Associates the the physical internal
states with the sufficient statistics of
these basian beliefs and there's a
lovely story you know in mathematics um
that would take you down the path of
information geometries and cisal
manifolds and um belief updatings as
movements in these geometries and you
know try to down the the metrics in
these spaces and how that relates to
uncertainty and precision all all that's
a lovely story um we don't need to
really pursue that at the moment the key
point being made here that the
generative model um is not physically
instantiated other than in terms of some
uh sufficient statistics in any setting
um however in the in the free energy
principle the generative model is in of
itself never actually instantiated in
terms or realized in terms of um its um
statist sufficient statistics and that's
because of something that we were
talking about before which is the
Dynamics so the Dynamics is a gradient
flow um which means that all we need are
the gradients of the free energy so we
don't need the generative model all we
need is the gradients of this free
energy function or F technically a
function or a function of a function
of the generative model
so if I was building an artifact I could
certainly prescribe the right Dynamics
by writing down a generative model and
then I could evaluate the gradients of
that um of that um free energy function
of the generative model and then those
gradients would actually drive the
Dynamics I could simulate
self-organization I could simulate
active inference I could simulate belief
sharing whatever I wanted to do
um but in that simulation all I really
needed were the gradients of the free
energy uh and we only need the
generative model because the um the free
energy is a function of the generative
model so in that sense the generative
model is really a t logical description
that you would bring to the table to
understand your sense making of another
thing um the thing in of itself just
needs the free energy gradients it just
needs to self-evidence by moving in the
direction of maximizing the on average
the log evidence for some abstraction
which is a generative model um but it
doesn't need to know that um um just to
you know so we don't confuse people so
moving up those log evidence uh
gradients very much like um you know
paradoxically moving up uh concentration
gradients to Clump together to keep in
this attracting set and to resist the
dispersion of the random fluctuations
inherent in these random dynamical
systems is just the same as moving down
the negative log evidence which is the
um um the uh the free energy itself it's
it's it's it's the same thing so what
does that mean well it um what it means
is the jint model is something that you
bring to the table to um endow
the behavior of this thing with an
explainable
teleology um of the kind it looks as if
this thing is acting in a way to
maximize the evidence or gather the
evidence for its generative model and
this is what I think its generative
model is but notice the thing in of
itself doesn't go through this process
um it could of course so if I now people
things like you and me
we we do have a model of mod we do have
um and we communicate it and we talk
about it but most things you know um um
um uh most things would not would would
not possess that um that deep structure
so you can invoke hular you can invoke
self-modeling you can invoke um
um your
uh the kind of um not hermanus in in the
sense that you would normally um um end
up with an um you know with with an
infinite regress but you know the the
kind of metacognitive aspect that comes
from any deep or deeply
structured hierarchical generative model
you you you you can you can get that
sort of humulus like Detachment and
metacognitive uh perspective on things
but strictly speaking um you know the
generative model is is is is only
entailed by the den DCS and I should say
that you know this is probably best to
think about um you know applications of
the free energy principle in you know in
in um as being limited to simulating and
modeling and understanding other things
as opposed to oneself unless one's doing
a lot of self modeling um so so in that
sense you are
ascribing um a teleology a purpose um um
that would explain the behavior of
something that you're observing but
notice because you are observing it from
its point of view you are an external
State and from your point of view all
you can see is the Markoff blanket you
cannot see what's going on on the inside
so it is um it would be mathematically
impossible for you to ever know whether
what's going on on the inside is indeed
um
um describable as even a gradient flow
on a free energy functional um let alone
did it have its own internal model did
it had it have its own beliefs it just
looks like that from your point of view
because you'll never ever know by
definition if you knew then you would um
by definition have breached the markof
blanket and that thing would cease to
exist as the kind of thing that it was
before um I mean may sound obvious or it
may sound trivial um but I don't think
it is if you just look at people like me
who spend our entire lives trying to
peer through the Markoff blanket using
brain Imaging for example and you know
or people doing um um comparative
Anatomy by dissecting dead things um um
or by inventing new techniques to try to
to try and get uh you can never get
beneath the Markoff blanket but you can
certainly sort of um have certain
perspectiv on the markof blanket that
are closer and closer to the internal
States but you can never actually get in
there I mean you know there's I imagine
a whole philosophy on this that you you
you couldn't um see your own um visual
processing you couldn't hear your own
colear Dynamics um
you you you you can't um ever have
access to the inside very much in the
spirit that internally would say you can
never have direct access to the outside
um so I think that also applies to these
stories about generative models and the
basy mechanic interpretation of uh that
comes along with the uh with the free
energy principle does that help in some
way it's a little bit subtle and I can
just imagine a lot of my friends tearing
their hair out because they have very
particular views about this yeah some
people think it's it's a model of a
model some people think it's you're
taking very internalist some people
external
mathematically um you know it's it's not
the model which drives drives as you
know it is the it is the Dynamics which
drives us and that Dynamics can be
interpreted in relation to a generative
model should you want
to excellent well I'm gonna follow that
philosophical line of thinking
and what I want to ask is this is an
interesting point that the notion that
we can get to a closer approximation of
what the internal States of
ourselves are for example but it's
always going to be an approximation
because piercing the mark of blanket
would constitute self disintegration
under the under the uh rules of or the
principle the free energy principle per
se how how in a sense therefore do we
know or or how how how uh how much can
we even make the claim therefore that
there is such a thing as an external
Dynamic that goes beyond anything goes
beyond our sensory in puts um it may
seem like a deeply non-scientific
question but um you the way you were
speaking couldn't I couldn't help but
think of people like George Barkley and
even Canton this phenomenal Nal
distinction if we don't ever have direct
access to so-called external
Dynamics because that is part and parcel
of the the physical game that we're in
why can't we just say that there are no
hidden States and all we get are
probability distributions over sensory
appearances but we don't need something
like a likelihood mapping to something
that's
latent
um well you you you you could say that
and a lot of my friends do say that um
and I think in the sense that um the the
notion of direct access means that um
you will never know in some sort of
fistic sense um what the external states
are if they exist at all and and um um
on the other hand you could also argue
um that um there is profound access to
the um and existentially meaningful
access to the external States it's just
organized in such a way that it it has
to be transacted by the Markoff blank
blanket um so you know I haven't I
haven't this conversation for for for
several
years now so I used to have lots of Pat
answers which um depending on who who I
was talking to but the the you the way
that you phrase a question which was
very clever um this made me think well
you know what is the internalist
argument does it mean that because I
don't have direct access that the
external states don't directly influence
me that means that they don't exist um
is is you know is that the the argument
that an internalist would make well may
might it be the case that all we have we
we don't need to invoke a kind of
further realm a further causal realm an
underlying ontological realm if all we
have are just the streams of sensory
input and seemingly some regularities
some patterned regularities in them why
at least in terms of doing the basian
modeling do we need to invoke a hidden
State an underlying cause for examp like
if we just take that if look at the low
road TCT of inflence we talk about how
human we talk about how cognitive
creatures like ourselves predict the
world let's say at a very simple level I
a question I've always had is why do we
why does the claims to predictive
processing or predictive coding more
generally why does it make claims about
hidden States why doesn't it make claims
just about regularities within streams
of appearances that's the way that I
would pose that
question right um
so I'm just mindful you've introduced uh
predictive coding and predictive
processing we have
we perhaps it would just just to for
those people um who may not uh know that
the the intimate relationship between
all these things so another way of
looking at free energy is it's the uh
amount of prediction error and more
specifically if you're talking to some
people it would be the uh the total
amount a Precision weighted prediction
error um which means that there's
another reading of minimizing free
energy which is not the maximizing the
model evidence but um minimizing
surprise where surprise is the
implausibility of some sensory data um
given your model of that data so in
exactly the same way that if I go around
Gathering data that I find uh
continuously
surprising um then that's basically
evidence I haven't got the right kind of
model to be um to be able to explain I.E
predict those those data um so again we
have one of these um um sort of
completely equivalent descriptions but
you know that have very different uh
flavors that to maximize model evidence
is to minimize surprise which is to
minimize a prediction error which is to
maximize predictability which is to
minimize very free energy and so on and
so forth they're all the same they're
all the same thing so when you're
talking about productive coding as a
particular um algorithm for minimizing
free energy uh technically um you know a
variational scheme which is known in
engineer as a Calon filter um what
you're saying is I'm making certain
assumptions um about my generative model
um that means I can write down these fre
energy gradients as prediction errors so
literally the prediction error my my Po
the Precision weighted prediction error
literally is mathematically exactly the
gradient that we were talking about
before um so just join the dots um so to
come back to your question um uh why is
it that um I need to invoke latent
States in order to make sense of data um
I would argue um that the sense making
is just explaining data in terms of
Laten States um and those latent states
are often referred to in um you know in
the technical literature as hidden
States and what do you mean by that well
it just means they're unobservable from
the point of view of the free energy
principle they are hidden behind the
mark of blanket so I would say that
detecting patterns simply is invoking
latent states that organize and
structure those patterns um so um I
don't think there's anything magical
about about latent States so the latent
states that are if you like entertained
by your internal Dynamics and your sense
making um uh are not the external States
you they are descriptions that are only
relevant to the generative model that um
you need in order to define the
prediction errors or the free energy
gradients in order to um you know
simulate or describe um your sense
making in terms of your neuronal
Dynamics or your internal Dynamics or
the operations of say a thermostat but
there's a Twist here um there's a reason
it's called active inference because
it's got a big active at the front um so
it's not good enough just to say oh I
can understand psychology just as making
lots of sense of my sensory
Impressions that's that's not good
enough um because you know you are um
coupled to the world um in in in
reciprocally which means that you
actually um are not only are you exposed
to the world but the world is exposed to
you in an exactly symmetrical way and
what would that um you know how could
one describe that and then we come back
to where where we started with this
partition of blanket States into sensory
and active States into the inputs and
the outputs um which means that sense
making is quintessentially active so one
way of phrasing that is that yes I'm
making sense of all this sensory data
and all the patterns um but at the same
time I'm actually in charge of and
actively soliciting those data causing
those patterns um so I think once you um
once you bring that sort of inactive um
aspect to the table so notice um I Noti
that you you you treated predictive
coding as a as a sort of generalization
predictive process in it might be easier
if you did the other way around because
then you have the grace to um
accommodate action in predictive
processing its most General sense and if
you don't then predictive processing you
know I think is an incomplete story you
have to have um as part of the
processing the active solicitation the
um the garnering and the structuring and
quering the world in a way that
reciprocates with the right kind of
information that allows you um to do the
good sense making in terms of um you
know the latent states that we that
we're talking about um I mean forly I
this takes us um into another part of
the story we didn't previously unpack
about active inference so somebody might
ask well Okay so we've got this um um
application of a um a free energy
principle that a physicist might be
quite comfortable with um to um behavior
that entails some kind of sense making
um cheekily with you know I like to call
this sening Behavior then I get told off
for that um but um so uh so how does
this differ from um reinforcement
learning you know how how how you
behavioral psychology um it differs in a
quite fundamental way U because the big
thing that active inference brings to
the table is is that um first of all it
says you are in charge you are actively
uh sensing you say this is Active Vision
active perception active inference in
this most General sense um which means
now what are the imperatives for
generating your own data now you could
if you were doing behavior of psychology
you of of a behaviorist sort in the 20th
century you could say well I just want
to generate those Sensations that I
found I'm rewarding um and so I got some
um privileged sensory um channels that
um I'm going to label as as reward and
I'm just going to act in a way that
maximizes the reward that comes in from
the point of view of the free energy
principle that's not what that's not
what happens what happens is I want to
find those data that resolve the
expected surprise or the expected free
energy consequent on acting soliciting
those data so what's expected surprise
well technically it's an entropy it's
just a measure a mathematical measure of
uncertainty so what that means is that
the um the the description of things
that persist or exist over some
particular period of time um reduces now
to a kind of basing mechanics in which
the behavior will look as if it is
information seeking and uncertainty
resolving um it will look as if it is
responding to these epistemic
affordances under constraints and it is
those constraints that um um if you like
would be the homologue of the reward um
they are literally the constraints
endowed by the prize on The generative
model the kind of um sensory states that
that constitute this attracting set you
know to which I am attracted but the the
vast majority um of the drives for good
um good behavior or sort of behavior
that things that exist would evince um
is this resolution of uncertainty this
information seeking and indeed you know
um that leads you into considerations
well what what is the how would you
describe that kind of information that
optimal uh information seeking behavior
um if you were a scientist or um if you
were an engineer and if you were a
scientist you'd be looking at the
principle of optimal basium design um
articulated by people like Dennis
Lindley in the middle of the last
century um where you measure the quality
of an action in terms of the Information
Gain afforded by the data that you
secure by acting in this way exactly the
same idea um um emerged in the context
of active learning in machine
learning you know this is the problem if
getting data is costly what data point
would I need to resolve the greatest
uncertainty about my um beliefs about
the latent causes of those data um so
Active Learning again notice actives uh
your actives um your um an explicit part
of this process
so in answer to your question about you
know would it be sufficient just to
understand
sentience in its most basic or Elemental
um
form as discovering patterns in data I
would say no um because that
denies the
openness of Any Given system immersed in
her World um in two directions you know
the world influencing you and you
influencing the world and since you put
that into the mix I think it's very
difficult to conceive of any construct
um possibly not in in philosophy um but
certainly any construct in computer
science or um um uh or physics that
would um
um that would permit a complete
description of senting behavior just in
terms of sensing
patterns does that make sense yeah yeah
that makes sense that makes sense um
makes sense to me um yes I want to stay
on action for a second because I
think the the notion of uh the
minimization of free energy or the
maximization of mod 11 makes some uh
could make some intuitive sense for an
agent like ourselves in the sense that
we we have our sensory inputs which are
Divergent from our prior and we act to
change the world to make those those
sensory outcomes more in line with our
expectations our
preferences however at a more
fundamental level uh one one definition
that we spoke about the free energy
principle is that the internal and
external States look like they're
tracking one another across a mark of
blanket now a question that comes to my
mind when when I see a definition like
that which is I that makes sense for me
uh for a sentient conscious human but
what would a stone be tracking or what
would a drop of oil be tracking to use
an example that you've um used before I
think so using going to something a bit
more less animate and I presume the
answer lies in
animacy um I think would be a really
interesting Avenue to go down because it
gets these fundamental questions of how
does something as minimal as a particle
retain its
particl and and and what does that
really look like when when we don't when
we presume that they're not conscious
unless we're pan pists but we won't go
just down that route just
yet well that's where you were taking us
which which
is a fun place to be um right how does
how does one um elude pan psychism in
the free energy principle I well I think
you you've just you've just uh answered
your own question there but so perhaps
we just unpack that a little bit um yeah
so what's the difference between a stone
um and a
thermostat
and and and me um and I think what
you're what you're now asking is um are
there um what I will call Natural kinds
but I wasn't allowed to because that has
a lot of philosophical baggage but for
the purpose of this conversation I'll
just say are the natural kinds of things
um that display different kinds of
behavior
that can that can be equipped with
different kinds of teeology and I would
say absolutely uh and you've just
rehearsed
you key so as you noted um to be animate
um is a big thing um in the sense that
the stone is not animate um in the sense
that it moves itself you know Stones
started you know wandering uphill or
flying around that would be much more
interesting
um but they don't have that animacy that
is characteristic of biotic self
organization so what does that mean in a
sort of um deflationary sense of the
free energy it just means that the
active states are an empty set um and
usually um for Stones you might also
argue the internal states are empty but
you don't have to yeah the stone can be
um you know making sense of its World in
terms of its latent States or can
acquire that inter interpretation
perhaps that's a nice example of what we
were trying to get um drill down on
earlier on in terms of um is a
generative model I mean I one could
argue that a stone has a generative
model of external mure in terms of the
temperature and the latent variable
which is a hidden State it's a latent
State you as well known in statistical
thermodynamics which is a a sufficient
statistic of the distribution of things
and the temperature uh um could well be
uh inferred by the internal the interior
of a stone and therefore it is making
sense of the pattern of its sensory
exchanges with the world on on the
surface of the stone simply because it's
warming and Cooling and therefore
tracking the ambient environmental
temperature so that's perfectly free
energy principle consistent um it's a
very boring kind of uh of sense making
but you know and it is that boring kind
of sense making that I had in mind when
talking about um if you preclude the
active part of active inference and just
think about sort of perceptual inference
um then then you're sort of missing the
point really um but I think a stone is a
good example of that now would you say
the stone has a generative model well
you could you could argue that but uh
you know it's you trying to trying to um
if like explain the behavior of a stone
but the stone doesn't have very much
behavior um but you could you could
start to think well now I can test a
hypothesis it is is actually registering
um uh the the temperature on the inside
and again just to rehearse the argument
the fundamental argument we were talking
about before you will never know though
until you break the stone because once
you brok the stone it's no longer a
stone it's just a broken Stone uh so
you're exactly the same problems or
issues confront you even with the stone
but you know focusing on on that sort of
big move from things with and without
active States I think then you're
talking about things that are animate
things that have um animacy and act upon
the world um is that sufficient to get
the kind of behavior that we've been
talking about which is um you know the
kernel of active influence in terms of
um what active influence brings to the
table in term in terms of uh information
seeking and having a variety of
different affordances particularly
epistemic affordances um as an
explanation for for for um for behavior
um you could argue no you a
thermostat can act upon the world it can
switch heating elements on or off and it
senses things by it by its Thermo
receptors and uh you could say like very
much like a wats governor um it you know
it now has active States it has inputs
and outputs and it has internal Dynamics
and um um and in one sense the wats
governor is a good regulator and
therefore conforms to um the cybernetic
view of of of of a generative model and
it's acting in the right kind of way so
does this kind of system um have that
the Curiosity that would be associated
with information seeking and resolving
uncertainty and you would argue well no
it doesn't so now you got another kind
of natural kind um which does so what's
the difference between you know a what's
Governor or a thermostat or possibly a
virus and um and me well I think the key
differen is a particular kind of um
self-modeling that just comes from being
very big and a bit structurally
complicated in the sense that there are
certain parts inside my body and inside
my brain that are so distant from the
active states that are actually moving
um my arm my actuators or um are
engaging my autonomic
reflexes that I cannot see them
directly um and if that is the case the
only way that I now can sense the
consequences of my action is vicariously
through the sensory States now this
introduces a really interesting
distinction between me and a virus it
means that I now will start to treat my
own action as a hidden or latent cause
of my
Sensations and that brings to the table
okay well if now my own action is being
inferred as a random variable then now
is a separation between what I think I'm
doing or what my active inference um um
would um allow me to talk about in terms
of what I what I'm planning to do or
what I'm inferring to do in the spirit
of planning as inference and what I'm
actually doing so this um brings you to
an even more a different kind of thing
which would be something like me um that
now has beliefs about um its own
action um which is distinct from the
actual real variables you know um that
constitute the active states of the
markof blanket um and as soon as I have
beliefs about my own action I have to
ask myself well as a physicist I would
ask well
what how what what are the probability
distributions over my um my active
States my um those states that um
actually change the causes or the um the
the external States generating my
Sensations and when you write that down
um what you get is exactly what we're
talking about before which is this
mixture of expected Information Gain
basically expected free energy that has
come be decomposed into this information
seeking part and the constraints
afforded by your prior uh the prior part
of your generative model the things that
you find very surprising per just to
unpack that um um intuitively you know
let's take the predictive processing
surprise minimization view of um self
organization and um an active inference
and that means that I now have the pro I
am the kind of creature that exists
therefore I must be minimizing my
surprise furthermore I now have beliefs
about my actions I have pry beliefs I
must have pry beliefs about my actions
of course this is all subpersonal so
what kind of Prior would I have about my
my own actions well I'm going to um
because I exist and I'm a um a free
energy surprise minimizing kind of thing
because I exist then I must choose those
actions that minimize the surprise I
expect following that action so that
means I'm going to minimize my expected
surprise now there are two ways in which
I can do that and we've already uh
spoken explicitly about the two ways one
way is just to notice that the average
surprise the expected
surprise um is just uncertainty so I can
reduce my expected surprise or my
anticipated or my um average um surprise
um by um getting to grips and knowing
you know what would happen if I did that
uh with greater Precision so this is
information seeking this is the sort of
the Curiosity um it's the novelty
seeking part it is the exactly the part
that underwrites the um the basic the
principles of optimum basian design
getting the data that minimize my
uncertainty because uncertainty just is
expect surprise but there's another way
of doing minimizing expected surprise if
I know what is very
surprising if you know by being um um at
very very low temperatures or being very
poor or being snubbed socially um
everything that is if you like not
characteristic of me given that I am you
know I exist in you in a particular way
um then any deviations of that basically
uh can be thought of surprising so if I
Stray Beyond very much in the spirit of
um homeostasis although now we're
talking about Al estasis because we're
talking about the future um then I'm
going to choose those actions don't just
uh do the information seeking responding
to the epistemic affordances but also
will elude those kinds of surprising
states that are very uncharacteristic of
me being very poor missing out on that
opportunity uh being embarrassed uh
being in pain um although pain is
probably a bad example we're talking
about the sensations that that we want
to want to avoid so um that would speak
to this um um the prior um the prior
cost or the prior surprise the negative
which was was the preferences you you
mentioned before so um you can look at
these constraints afforded by the prior
the pragmatic part if you like of um of
these affordances some people call them
instrumental so you got epistemic and
instrumental um affordances that just
are the expected Information Gain and
the negative expected cost which would
be the um your manifestation of the
constraints you could look at the the
complement of constraints in terms of
where I don't go in my sensory State
space um as um where I do go which are
my preferences my preferred
characteristic attract attracting sets
so uh just to remind myself and and you
and people who are listening still at
this stage um why are we going through
all this well because this is what comes
out
of a
consideration of beliefs PR beliefs
about the way active State Should unfold
uh how and that becomes very pertinent
when now I have to actually um embody
those beliefs in my generative model so
suddenly now I become something that is
very distinct from a thermostat or or a
virus because now I have a generative
model of the consequences of my action
and that generative model is very simple
it just says a priori I will um a priori
think that the action that maximizes
information gain and maximizes this
instrumental value uh are going to be
the most likely policies and this you
you know could be construed as a um a
high-end kind of planning as inference
it's not as trivial or simple as a sort
of uh K control because we've got this
epistemic part part part of it but it
still has a spirit of planning of
inference so what I'm saying quite
simply is there are certain things that
plan and there are certain kinds of
things that don't plan a virus doesn't
plan the weather doesn't plan Evolution
doesn't plan the stone doesn't plan and
you could argue that many um um smaller
insects don't plan but as you get bigger
things then they start to plan and I
think you move from non-planning to
planning at which point by definition
you are ascribing to these bigger things
like you and me um a be
ascribing um a teeology to our behavior
that rests upon a generative model that
includes the consequence es of its own
action which crucially equips it with a
temporal depth because the consequences
are in the future so unlike the
thermostat that doesn't need to look
very far into the future things that
plan that are so big that they um lose
contact with their actual actuators um
now look as if they're they have this
sort of temporal depth and this this
temporal thickness to their generative
models specifically enabling them to PL
to uh plan in plan their actions in Into
the Future so that's how I would get out
of the pan psychism
argument okay I've never I've never
heard that argument before um about the
distance from the actuators that's very
interesting um because it seems in that
sense that the temporal depth is
Downstream on
size in a sense um is that is that a
correct reading and and is there a
reading of your argument that you've
just laid out there in which you can
have deep temporal model uh modeling
planning as
inference and um allostasis as well as a
sense of um retrospective inference
without being a large thing is that or
is this notion of being uh far from your
actuators so that you have to start
disambiguating what is your action and
what is the action of the world or other
people is that fundamental um yeah I
mean this this is a really interesting
notion because I've I've actually never
heard it really be uh elucidated like
that so I'd love to know whether there
is a way that a virus could be doing
deep temporal modeling despite its
minimal size right yeah I mean to be
honest I don't know um but a a a sort of
um an intuitive answer uh would be uh no
size really does matter it really does
matter so by size I I you know I'm
implicitly talking about the um the the
the sparse coupling that underwrites the
conditional dependencies in manical
systems that give rise to mark of
blankets and blankets and blankets so um
I'm not literally talking about you know
how how how wide something is in terms
of millimeters I'm talking about the
sort of um the hierarchical depth of of
um condition dependences and being
secluded behind markof blanket after
Markoff blanket after markof blanket so
um if you if you're comfortable
associating um physical size with that
um hierarchical depth in terms of um
what a thing is in you know in terms of
having this internal hierarchical
structure internal markof blankets then
I think the answer is very clear no you
have to have you have to be sufficiently
big so I'd be extremely Sur surprised um
so for example I haven't said this
before but you know I would imagine very
very small insects can't plan whereas um
something the size of a bee might be
able to plan so I'd imagine that a
droper couldn't plan but I I would
imagine a bee might just be able to get
there and it and it it starts um you
know first of all that that that
immediately speaks to a philosophical
vagueness in terms of that temporal
thickness which which which is
interesting I mean is it is it
categorical you know can I say this kind
of artifact um can be explained in terms
of a generative model that does not
cover its own action because has direct
access to its actuators because it's
sufficiently simple and small there are
no Markoff blankets that intervene
between the um the you know the um
effectively the the the sense making
part and the um uh and for example
sending predictions and the predictive
processing Spirit down to the um the
actuators um whereas this thing is so
big that there are inevitably with
probability one so many Markoff blankets
that intervene there is no now direct
access to action upon the world um and
um
so that might be a uh a bright line it
might be a um a qualitative distinction
between things that do and do not have
um
uh a representation of their own actions
um on the other hand the counterargument
I think would be this more vague notion
that that you even even a
thermostat could be ConEd as having a
little glimpse of the future simply
because it could be um cast as say a PID
controller which basically um um invokes
now rates of change and as soon as you
invoke rates of change you've got sort
of your know a mathematical image of a
little trajectory into the future so it
could be a great it could be a graded
thing I've lost I've lost what the
importance of your question what I ask
you a question again it was probably it
was probably unimportant
um but this is really sorry it
felt I'll go again this is a very
interesting line that I'd love to I'd
love to dive down into so what so my
interpretation of this my my reading of
this is that in a sense having bundles
of Markov blankets embedded in Markov
blankets leads to the inevitable
inference that there is something like
me which is doing something and there is
something that's not like me which is
also causing sensory um data that I'm
receiving that makes
sense
now let's let's tie in temporality to
this does it does this does this mean
that in a sense
temporality is a coroller of selfhood in
the sense that the selfhood is almost
more fundamental than the the
temporality because it comes from the
dimensionality of the things that are
Mark of blankets upon Mark of blankets
and how can we integrate temporality and
temporal thickness or depth um into this
picture right yeah that's absolutely
right and um you could tell the story in
a number of different ways you know if
you're talking to um for example Chris
fields or Maxwell ramstead and they
might start talking about um irreducible
Markoff blankets um that
necessarily uh require the notion of
nested Markoff blankets and that there
is some one or more core irreducible
Markoff blankets that would have um this
aspect of looking at one's one's own
inference processes and acting
internally and they get the notion of
mental action and you can then start to
work towards um sort of qualitative
experiences in terms of self-modeling
and what that might look like um the
other the other way that you could tell
this story is to know that um to invoke
um the renormalization group if you were
were we a physicist and just know that
when you're talking about any
hierarchical generative model there is
um inevitably a a COR graining that
includes time in that g in that depth um
which means very simply that the deeper
parts of my generative moral and indeed
a viruses are on a free energy principle
view um
um encoding beliefs about things that
change more and more slowly as you go
deeper and deeper so there's a
separation temporal scales um so you I a
common sensical view of this is that um
the the neuronal
representations uh down near my primary
auditory cortex or indeed in in in in
the brain stem um are representing very
very fast fluctuations in um pressure
and then frequencies and T and and sort
of scenographic like um um
representations that are changing um you
know possibly even in fractions of of a
millisecond if you're an owl um but
certainly over over 100 milliseconds
then I move up to sort of you know
primary auditory cortex and I may be in
the realm of sort of um hundreds of
milliseconds and sort of frequency
Glides that Define phones and I move up
to secondary auditory coures and then
through the auditory hierarchy getting
to the level of um um words right up to
um say you know some parts of prefrontal
Cortex where we've gone
entire semantics and syntax and
narratives and stories start to emerge
and as every time we go deeper into the
hierarchy we slow down or we extend the
temporal Compass thereby providing a
context for the faster influences and
fluctuations at the level below so again
we come to this um you know notion of um
size
entailing um a um a a certain kind of
depth in this instance a hierarchical
depth in the generative model that as
you say necessarily goes in hand in hand
with a temporal depth and a separation
of temporal scales so I think you're
absolutely right there has to be a
temporal aspect to deep generative
models and by Deep I just mean that
there are nested Markoff blankets so you
know to define a hierarchy is only
defined in terms of the conditional
independences um and implicitly the
Markoff blankets of one level in the
hierarchy um that defines it as a level
in the hierarchy without the mark of
planket the hierarchy would not be there
so that's another example of this sort
of um
um being open but being closed um
um being able to individuate something
from something else and and this is as
if the thing is just the level of a
hierarchical a hierarchal generative
model that we're ascribing to um the
Dynamics of of some internal of some
internal States I think there's a third
story you could tell which is possibly
where you're going which is um um how it
relates to to Consciousness um um in the
sense and this is a very simple story
that that that um if I am
um forming beliefs and doing
um belief basing belief updating as
prescribed by active
inference about the consequences of my
actions then that has to be in the
future as we' just said and perhaps
certain things think deeper into the
future than than other things um but
notice what we've done here it's about
my actions so not only have you
committed to temporality um and temporal
depth and temporal thickness as an
attribute of things that plan um and are
more like you and me but you've also
committed to agency so now you've
created from something that was
previously not an agent into an agent
where I'm using agency in the sense that
I one would not say that a thermostat
had agency but you would say that I have
agency um in the sense that I have
beliefs
about the consequences of my action and
I um will or can be described as um
using those beliefs to select a
particular action and you know coming
back to predictive coding formulations
that that selection would basically I'm
going to predict the state of my um
Motor plant or my autonomic um nervous
system and provide with the right set
points and and then the the active stat
will actually reflexively fulfill those
prophecies those predictions um and
everything is working properly I'll I'll
be a good Alat or in R's terms a good
hom homat um so what what you've done
there is is bring agency into the game
um and I think that again this speaks to
the inactive part that you know you now
because you've got beliefs about the
future and specifically the future that
you have caused that you have authored
you have now become an agent so we have
I think got this this stage to
Consciousness and self-awareness but I
think we've got the necessary Foundation
that there are only certain things that
have to be agents I think to be
conscious of themselves as agents as
doing things um as things that exist in
um um in a world uh in the sense that
their existence is Manifest in terms of
the consequences of the way that they
act upon that world if it wasn't you
wouldn't need any of this you wouldn't
need this temporal thickness you just be
you you you just need the apparatus of a
stone or a thermostat to make to do do
your sense making but as soon as you got
agency in the game I think then you've
got you've got something which takes a
step closer to um having a very deep and
possibly it's this irreducible Markoff
blanket um um um layer of the generative
model or level of a of a deep generative
model which actually now starts to
entertain the hypothesis
I am an agent um which you don't need
but you could and you have to ask
yourself why would you ever want to
entertain that hypothesis I am an agent
um so this would be minimal selfhood
just a
representation um that I can be in
different states of mind when it uh that
and those states of Mind are something
that underwrite or I can condition on it
in terms of what I'm going to do and
that doing could be internal it could be
how I deploy attention in terms of
precision weighting in predictive coding
coding um so it could be covert action
or it could be overt action I could now
um select um you know um certain plans
at a lower level that would be then um
enacted by my motor system or my
autonomic system if I was that that kind
of
creature does that make
sense it makes sense and there open up a
can of worms in my head um well
inevitably because we brought in lots of
Concepts here and I want to try and
unpick them um for people at home and
for myself but it's fascinating so I'm
loving it so let's keep going along this
along this road we've got agency
Consciousness and
temporality as as these three things I
want to have a little look
at starting with the first thing we talk
uh you you mentioned as a response to my
question about
temporality that we have a deep
hierarchy in which um more deeper levels
of the hierarchy are
tracking um slower fluctuations in the
external Dynamics and therefore
contextualize and constrain the higher
order faster
Dynamics is it are we in this model are
we invoking time as a fundamental aspect
of the external Dynamics or is it an
inference that the act that the um that
the organism is making about the nature
of reality that it's
experiencing um well that's that's again
an excellent question it's certainly um
does not um
um it does not address time perception
uh in terms of the psychophysics of time
perception um does it address um time in
in a more fundamental sense I I don't
think it does um in a sort of um sort of
folk psychological sense um it's really
um so the the answer to that question
normally um is framed in terms of
relative movements in a belief space um
and um so if you think of time as um
part of some Metric space time then what
you're talking about is time as
something that can be measured time that
has a a distance say milliseconds or
seconds on the like um could me um could
me as a generative model um
um ever have access to or build um
hypotheses uh of time as a metric yes we
certainly could um how however um it
would be very difficult um you're
ignoring sort of internal clocks and the
like well actually no you have to ignore
internal clocks you then ask how do you
do it and normally what what the story
the story is um it's the the number of
moves you make at one level relative to
another level of a deep generative model
and the number of moves is quite crucial
here in terms of tying that down
mathematically um and my favorite way of
thinking about the number of moves is
basically something called the
information length and the information
length um refers back to something we've
mentioned before which is information
geometry so as if you think of our um so
one picture of the free energy principle
it's quite a technical picture but I
think it's quite useful is that um our
internal say brain States or the
internal states of a thermostat um
encode a probability distribution a Bas
in belief a conditional belief about
some latent States um which means that
for every state of the brain there is if
you like a point in the state space of
all the physical states of the brain but
each point in that space now stands in
for a probability
distribution and that means that um this
is a special kind of space because it is
equipped with a metric what is that
metric well it's the K Divergence well
the pathal infantes small K divergences
as I move through the space so this is
what this is what defines information
geometry the the information geometry is
a very particular um bit of
mathematics um or theorizing that
applies to very very special State
spaces or manifolds where every point in
that on that manifold corresponds to a
belief or a probability distribution so
now what if the metric
is the um the K Divergence or you know
the information length which is related
to the um the accumulated K divergences
as I move from one point to another um
what we are saying is that the um the
number of moves I make the number of
units as measured with the the um this
kind of metric this information
geometric uh measure um which actually
technically is this official information
um is is um basically um a description
of um the
Precision by which I measure whether
I've changed my mind so if we say that
I've made n moves that means I've
changed my mind end times and I know
that because I can measure the
information length and I've actually
moved a a
significant by a significant um or by a
measure that is large simply because it
is large in relation to the Precision
that
uh that provides the distance between
any two points on this so what that
means to put it very simply is that time
can be measured by the number of CH
times I change my mind at level n in my
hierarchy divide divided by the number
of times I change my mind at the lower
level
so now you've got a relational uh you
can gauge time by the relative degrees
of belief updating you know um the
information rate which is the you know
um um um confusingly the the the rate of
change of the of the length with with
time but where time is now uh
contextualized by the level above or or
by the level below so you have this very
relativistic view of time um and you
could have different levels you know I
would imagine um if you you attend to
different levels of your hierarchy you
could get a very different kind of time
perception indeed we know that
attentional set and um um in conditions
where um say taking psychedelics or uh
in things like Parkinson's disease where
where you get um changes in the
neurobiological encoding of uncertainty
and therefore this fishal information
metric you can get distortions and
different senses of time um so what I'm
saying is there are probably as many
different senses of time as there are
levels in a hierarchical model and it
can only really be measured in a in a
relative sense in terms of how many
moves do I make at one level in for any
given move at another
level so um that the what we've done now
is if you like um take take temporality
off the table to the extent now that
we're now just talking about uh
movements in an information space or a
belief space that has this kind of
information
geometry these are really fascinating
issues uh I think yet to be fully
explored um my my friend zaf um um has
done probably some of the best work in
in um in this area um but you know it is
it is to my mind um a really interesting
issue because you it really forces you
to think about the um what you mean by
separation temporal scales and what we
what what kind of course grading over
time is implicit in this kind of move
from one level to uh to the next level
does that address your what you were
what you
were yeah I mean as I was saying this is
all really interesting um and again
something I hadn't thought of um before
in terms
of in terms of this in terms of this
contextualization process being about
moves which implies to me that but there
has to be like this sense of time is
contingent on these moves that are being
done at the different levels of the
hierarchy does that process itself not
imply some Dynam some temporal Dynamics
how can one
distinguish a move of 10 relative to a
move of five without having segmented
moves in some kind of space-time
geometry yes and it is exactly that um
segmentation that appeals to the
information geometry um so yeah how
would you actually do that segmentation
how how would you measure um the amount
of belief updating um in Universal or
clock time um at one level of a
hierarchy and um this is where the
information geometry comes in it's
basically the number of different brain
states that you have entertained during
your movement on this statistical
manifold which is also you know I think
very nicely articulated in terms of
belief updating so you can literally
think of this sort of um the space that
would be traced out if I were to plot um
the activity of all my neurons um on
every axis of some very high dimensional
State space that would be a statistical
manifold my belief updating which is a
continuous process my gradient flow um
is literally moving on this manifold the
distance I move is the information
length that literally scores the degree
to which I change my mind it's also
mathematically The Information Gain um
as measured well closely related to the
information gain as measured by the K
Divergence between my prior and my
posterior after I do my belief updating
and I'm moving on this manifold and the
question question is you know how far
have I moved U and can I segment segment
that into units and that's basically
what the information length um you know
allows you to do so I I love this
picture because um if you just think
about what kind of flows on this
manifold would um be prescribed by the
free energy
principle because the free energy is a
functional of the uh beliefs
um encoded at each point then the free
energy is a landscape on the statistical
manifold so we are perpetually falling
downhill on this manifold the the free
energy gradients are themselves and the
free energy is itself changing because
my beliefs are changing so I've got this
lovely itinerant you know model or
picture in mind where I've got a cical
manifold it is now um where I have
gradient flow
where I'm flowing on this manifold um
using a gradient flow on free energy
where the free energy now provides a
wadington like landscape chasing Minima
all the time and of course that chasing
reflects the fact that the free energy
itself changes as you move around the
manifold because your beliefs are
changing and the free energy is uh a
function of belief um and then you
introduce this uh this notion which I
think is really important um
the notion that the high level of a a
deep model um provides the context and
what would the context look like in
terms of this free energy landscape well
it means that the landscape would change
so you know I've got this gradient flow
which is um um from um on a fast time
scale just flowing down the
landscape down the landscape but at the
slow level the landscape is itself now
changing all the time so I'm perpetually
chasing Minima um and moving Minima
because the gradients themselves are
contextualized and are changing slowly
so you get this deep structure to the
temporal Dynamics um which has this very
non-markovian aspect so now we've got
this interesting picture where things
like you and me that are big where big
just means that there are lots of
Markoff blankets that um constitute my
deep generative model
um that enable this um separation of
time scales um you've got this picture
um where each level is now providing the
landscape for the level below with very
very fast changes but of course these
are now changing the
um the landscape is itself changing so
that now you've got a non-markovian
model of a universe that we know is
maravian um so we know because we
started if you remember right at the
beginning with this notion of a random
dynamical system that is usually
associated with uh things like a lan
equation or you know a maravian process
um so we're starting from a a
maravian um Universe with effectively no
memory and now we've found things inside
this universe that look as if they found
a non- maroven explanation a coar
grained sense um sensible and sense
making explanation for their sensory
Impressions that is quintessentially
non- maroven that has this deep temporal
structure of the kind you find in
language yeah the whole point of say for
example um you know hierarchal derish um
um process models of natural language
right through to the uh current focus on
Transformer architectures in large
language models they're all about
breaking the maravian um they're all
about finding non- maravian explanations
for what at the end of the day must be
uh you know a a Marco a maravian process
and you may ask where does that come
from well um if we spend most of our
time trying to model um input where that
input is generated by things like does
and we are complex deep things that
generate non-markovian actions then in
fact our universe now becomes non-
maravian simply because we have other
things in it that are sufficiently big
to have these deep generative
models and then you get into language
and and communication and uh you know
the itinerancy which is I think quite
unique to us you know I don't think
you'll find this kind of Dynamics if you
get too big um and certainly as we've
already discussed it it can't exist at a
very microscopic scale so even in your
head um your macro molecules in the 16th
um dendrite in the ca1 field of your
left hippocampus that doesn't do any
planning it's too small uh it doesn't
have that requisite depth of or nesting
of Markoff blankets um uh so small stuff
can't do got have this separation of
temporal scales and this particular deep
itinerancy and
sort of um you know Marium breaking like
property but interestingly when you get
too big um you also can't do it either
so you know the motion of the heavenly
bodies the uh the moon and the and the
Sun and the like they don't plan um and
you know it's interesting ask well why
not well because they don't have um
because a lot effective because they're
so big all the random fluctuation in
their world have gone away and you now
um are left with classical mechanics so
you know you could sort of get
terministic chaos in end body problems
but there wouldn't be a
description um that would um be usefully
interpreted in terms of planning as
inference or active inference in the way
that we've been talking about so I think
there's a Goldilocks regime you got to
be big enough but not too big uh to do
this to do this kind of planning
wow amazing yeah I mean it's um it's
bringing up all of these existential
potentially fluffy questions in my mind
um which I I I would like to sort of ask
at least one which is we could ask why
let's take the macro structures the
celestial
bodies black hole universe itself we
could ask why why in a mechanistic
mathematical sense do they not um have
this kind of non- Marian temporal
Horizon so there's a mathematical answer
to that which or a physical physical in
the sense of being explained by
physicists there's an answer to that
there isn't necessarily an existential
answer to that um and I guess I I do not
expect a concrete answer because I'm
sure there isn't one but Millennia has
been dedicated to the question of The
Human Condition and why maybe that
itinerancy is so fundamental defining of
our nature which is that we can't seem
to kind of sit still we are open and the
world is affecting us and we're
affecting the world as you said and
we're in this constantly Dynamic
coupling I guess I would love to just
hear intuitive thoughts that you might
have
on why the universe would unfold in such
a way that you do have a goldilock Zone
um why why is it the case that things
like
us have this one wondering
openness rather than just being um
either in the soup or being firmly rigid
forever if you have any thoughts on
that um you yeah not well formed
thoughts um but I mean it is a
fascinating thing to reflect upon um I I
think the answers that that someone like
me would give you would inherit from a
sort of um a classical view of um
physics as opposed to a Quantum
information theoretic view uh so you may
get a very different answer if you ask
somebody like um um Carlo relli or
Steven Wolfram or um you know my friend
Chris Fields um but if you're happy with
a sort of um 101 physicist's response uh
to that um the way that I would look at
that is through the lens of the
renormalization group which just says
that there the um the the things exist
at different scales and there is a um
you are um looking for explanations of
those that that that scale free behavior
in terms of laws that are dynamics or
lrin technically um uh that are
conserved um over different levels and
for for the free energy principle that
is just the um the Dynamics the gradient
flow on the um uh on the free energy
defined at each level or each scale um
and that leads you to then a view of um
the same kind of things sorry the same
kind of processes and the same
principles applying at each and every
Scale of the Universe so that you would
at a very very fine time scale and a
very very fine um um spatial scale so
the quantum scale you would have uh lots
of very very fast hot Stones moving
around uh where the random fluctuations
predominate um and there is very little
of this kind of long-term
itinerancy um now technically that
results from um um some as certain
aspect of the way that you can always
decompose any Dynamics any gradient flow
so I've spoken um about the Dynamics
exclusively in terms of gradient flows
flowing down um the uh flowing down the
uh the free energy landscape say on a
cisal manifold being my sort of favorite
picture of that
um that denies a real another really
important aspect of the flow which is
the flow orthogonal to that gradient
flow uh known as solenoidal flow or
Divergence free flow um so the way that
I look that I look at this um through
the lens of a sort of classical
physicist that that would predicate
everything on this random dynamical
system or Lan approach um is that you've
got a Continuum between the very small
and the very big where now we're not
talking so much um about sort of the the
degree of nesting of Markoff blankets
but simply the um the the contribution
of random fluctuations to the Dynamics
um and the important thing to bear in
mind is that there is any Dynamics any
flow has this solenoidal part this
conservative part and this dissipative
part that inherits from the random
fluctuations so if you're very very
small then all the random fluctuations
have not yet been averag away and the
dissipative part predominates over the
conservative part the solenoidal part um
which means that at the very very small
scales you are effectively in the world
of um thermodynamics where you're
effectively ignoring the uh the
solenoidal part um so everything is
disappeared you get fluctuation
dissipation theorems um you know um uh
inte intergral fluctuation theorems you
know and then you can drive
generalizations of the second law and
all of that good stuff um and then as we
as we get bigger and bigger and bigger
the what the course grining implicit in
the um what's known as um an RG operator
in the renormalization group sort of I
look at grouping and dimension
reductions a course graining uh or
entails an averaging and as you average
the random fluctuations average out to
zero
so now the the dissipated part
disappears and you just left with a
solenoidal flow which is just the
conservative dynamics of Newtonian
mechanics and leanan mechanics and the
solenoidal aspect is just a description
of like the moon going around the earth
and the earth going around the sun it's
things that have orbits stable orbits of
qu periodic um um orbits that are
approaching deterministic Sy they are
very very big so the interesting thing
happens in the Middle where you've got a
mixture of dissipative uh Dynamics and
conservative Dynamics what would the
conservative Dynamics look like well
they would look like this sort of um
itinerant um um um oscillation it would
look like the same kind of uh classical
conserved oscillation that the moon does
but it will be much more itinerant it'll
look like a a you know um a buyer Rhythm
it will look like a life cycle it will
look it will have that property that we
associate with living movement so you
know we talked before about the fact to
to
um to be autonomous is to move it is to
have active States one would also argue
that movement in and of itself is not
sufficient you know the moon moves um
the oceans move um are they biotic in
their self organization I think you'd be
looking now for a special kind of
movement which emphasizes the solonoid a
mixture of solenoidal and dissipative uh
dis dissipative Dynamics um so
sandwiched in between the very big and
the very small is a goldilock regime
where indeed you do have this
opportunity for the biotic kind of
self-organization that characterizes our
existence that is
um not only um manifest in terms of
delicately crafted solenoidal diversion
3 Dynamics but also nested at different
time scales so just think about all the
different time scales that your um body
entertains solenoidal Dynamics um um
rotational Dynamics from the fast gamma
oscillations again in that hippocampal
neuron through to um your um cardiac
cycle through to your respiratory cycle
through to the your dial Cycles through
to your um um slower Cycles right
through to your life cycle uh and so on
and so forth and then you take it up to
any scale you want um but the key thing
the point being made here is that not
only do you have this ad mixture of
disputed gradient flows that underwrite
self- evidencing this is in the Contex
text of this solenoidal flow at multiple
scales at nested scales so again we come
back to of this deep nesting um so on
that view there will be a Goldilocks
regime and of course it is only at that
in that regime will you ever get systems
that start to self- moral and
communicate and co-construct their their
niches will you get cultural Niche
construction will you get the kind of
would you get language and will you have
conversations like this it's not going
to happen um at the level of uh
macromolecules or cells and it's not
going to happen at the level of heavenly
bodies but it will happen at our level
um um uh and clearly has happened if I
can believe my
senses yeah I guess
the yes I guess the I mean my followup
my my inevitable followup would be why
are there these different sizes but I
don't I don't want to get into that book
it's just Turtles all the way down about
why I mean we we can bring it to CL very
quickly but that's it it is Turtles all
the way down that's I I think a
fundamental Insight uh and once you once
you commit to that everything starts to
make a lot more sense so um you know
just in terms of um you know how long
will my Markoff blanket last well it
will last the you know for a long time
at my temporal scale but the um the
scale above um will last much longer so
I have an environment and a niche that
lasts longer than I do and my body lasts
longer than anyone's cell and my cell
lasts lasts longer than any well
intercellular component and you know
that component will last longer than any
particular macromolecular uh
configuration so uh so it is all the way
down and you need it at each level you
have to have the context being a thing
having its own Markoff blanket at its
scale in order to um provide the context
for the faster coming and going of
Markoff blankets at the lower scale but
in the same sense because the larger
scale inherits from the dyamics of the
lower scale there's is a circular caety
which people like George Alice would
cast in terms of top down and bottom up
causation put simply what that means I
cannot exist well let's put it another
way my hippocampal cell cannot exist
unless my brain is in good shape my
brain cannot good shape unless I'm doing
good active influence and relating
correctly within my family and my consp
specifics my cons specifics cannot uh
work uh exist unless there is um a
biosphere that sustains that kind of
Life the biosphere cannot exist and and
so on and so forth all the way up and
all the way down and every Lev there are
things and those things have to have
Markoff blankets and at every level they
can be construed as doing some kind of
Elemental inference or self- evidencing
um the the story we're telling though is
the special kind of self- evidencing
that comes out at a particular scale but
the existence of that scale requires
exactly the same um I repeat from the
perspective of the renormalization group
it requires exactly the same Dynamics or
LR or functional form of the Dynamics um
at you know at every level and you know
on this view because the explanatory
Target or the free energy principle is
basically relational it's trying to
understand
self-organization um of a thing that can
be
individuated um in this context and in
terms of what it is
contextualizing it's a very myopic um
ambition it doesn't describe you know
cosmology or um you know the universe uh
you're not going to get electromagnetism
from the free energy principle um um um
and so it doesn't really have to worry
about when does this you know whe what
is the largest scale what is the
smallest scale you can keep on going all
the way down and if you had to headed
your bets because I guess it is a hedge
better bet hedger rather um does it stop
does does the is or is it just it just
goes on Mark of blankets on Mark of
blankets yeah
yes mathematically yes yeah there is
yeah it's a little bit like you asked me
uh where's the um um where's the edge of
the Earth when does the Earth
stop yeah if if if you're committed to
the renormalization group um now it just
keeps on going forever um that
um and you sort of I'm quite comfortable
with that because um you know it emerges
from a sort of of um a question which is
what is a state so we've been talking
gbly about State spaces cisal manifolds
and states of Affairs that hidden States
and latent States um to have a state
space and particularly specifically to
have a um a state space that be that can
be interpreted or construed as AAL
manifold you have to have States but
what what where do states come from
U and the argument sorry I shouldn't ask
you AR the argument is that they are the
states of things where the things come
from oh we just said it's a partition of
States space where did the states come
from and if you try to answer that
question um then you all you have to do
is basically um determine the mapping
between um things or particles and
states and the answer is quite simple it
is it is basically one way of looking at
this sort of um or using the appar
apparatus of the renormalization group
that um the the the state of a thing is
the uh state of its Mark of blanket
States um and then the um the then then
that state itself now has a Marian or a
a a partition into maroff blankets so
you now get blankets and blankets um and
so that you can resolve the par Parx or
the um the Catch 22 you know what's the
state of something well what's a thing
well a thing is determined by
conditional independen among the states
you know you can resolve that infinite
regress just by saying it is just a
recursion that you know States at one
level inherit the averages of the markof
blanket states of things at the next
level but the at every level there are
things so you have this um you know you
just keep on going down I should say um
you know there are people who believe
that um there is a smallest scale or it
is sufficient I'm not absolutely sure
about this but if you ever get the
chance in later life if you can talk to
uh again people like Carlo relli or
Steven wolam um you know from the point
of view of quantum luk gravity and from
the point of view of the ruad um then
the you know there is this notion that
there is some
irreducible um
um smallness scale Beyond which you
can't go and then the game is how do you
get a continuous world out of this sort
of quantum discret um um very very small
description of
things yes yeah yeah yeah yeah strange
Loops makes me think of Hof Stell and
strange Loops also makes me think
slightly of the um holographic principle
what you just mentioned there about
projections onto the screen um this this
this notion of um reading of the mark of
blanket you said something that I said
we had three things that I wanted to
talk about um and we covered temporality
all beit over a long temporal scale
wanted to very quickly ask you
mentioned um in passing um about
celestial bodies being nearly
deterministic and my ears pricked up um
I on an internalist model of the free
energy principle I sense that there's
actually a kind of Licensing for free
will because we have this internal model
and we act upon the world as to confirm
the model that we we wish to we wish to
observe on an externalist perspective
where we really are no different
from another physical entity except for
the fact that we have the possibility of
moving things and and acting to to
self-evidence there isn't so much space
for free will but my ears picked up when
you spoke about agency and when you
spoke about the celes your body's being
nearly deterministic because it makes me
think it seems to
imply at least uh
huris that being open to the environment
being an itinerant being
licenses agents agency but I want to
make sure this is true metaphysical
agency in the sense
of not hard
determinism um or whether this is agency
in the sense of
self-conception as a free agent because
those are two different things um it's
we won't be denying that we perceive
ourselves to be free I guess the fun the
more fundamental question there is
whether that's an illusion or not and so
I was wondering whether free energy
principle has anything to say about a
kind of libertarian versus deterministic
perspective on Free
Will um well I mean you could certainly
use the the the um the free energy
principle to tell stories that speak to
those arguments um and I think you
picked up on the some you know some of
the key parts of those stories um so you
know deterministic chaos that you get
with nbody problems when thinking about
so massive bodies dancing around each
other um you know there is still chaos
in mix in the mix um so there's an
unpredictability and sensitivity to
initial conditions in in the good
oldfashioned way of um non- dynamical
system System Theory of A deterministic
Sort um but once you get to um you know
things like you and me um you're really
in the world of stochastic chaos so the
stochastic bit inheriting from the uh
the random fluctuations where you've got
um two kinds of um if you like or two
aspects of uncertainty and implicitly
then in modeling that uncertainty um um
uh the opportunity to talk about sort of
Free Will and selection um one
interesting twist here is that the um if
you actually want to apply the free
energy Principle as a principle of least
action to things like you and me um what
you have to um um imagine is that we are
deterministic things in a sastic and
chaotic World um so in making sense of
things we only do so at a particular
scale we're talking before about the
averaging away when I'm sufficiently big
to average away my random fluctuations
under the free energy principle that
literally means you have to take the
average of lots of neurons so the kind
of sense making the kind of uh dynamics
that you would simulate under the free
energy principle applies to and only to
The Ensemble Behavior where you can
average away any of the stochastic
aspects so you will not get you will not
be able to deduce evidence or um um
solicit or um find evidence for the
freey principle by looking at single
neuron single synaptic it has to be at
the The Ensemble level where the the um
well there are all sorts of arguments
where that has to be the case but um
from from our point of view it's when
the random fluctuations are averaged
away um so I'm just qualifying what I'm
saying is I'm not saying that the brain
is stochastic or shows stochastic chaos
what I'm saying is that the brain has to
provide an apt explanation or
approximation um to explain stochastic
chaos um and crucially um the um
stochastic chaos associated with our own
behavior um with the consequences of our
own actions so you got a deterministic
system trying to now Model A
non-deterministic stochastic chaotic
system um and you know in so doing well
that's easy to do because of course
we're we're talking about um that
modeling being in terms of belief or
probability distribution so that that's
Absol abely no problem um so um on that
view I think you could easily motivate
um Free Will of a certain kind um in the
sense that you when are when you're
planning you have effectively to select
amongst different models of the future
technically this we Bas in model
selection and selection is an act and so
again we have a different kind of agency
here but it has it's a kind of agent
inherent in the selection amongst
competing plans or
policies narratives paths to into the
future um that I think has all the space
to um um say that this and it's you
doing the choosing remember you can't
there's nothing on the outside that can
influence directly that choice on the
inside so from your point of view you
certainly have free will would it look
like you have Free Will from the outside
um um I think that's a more vexed
question uh of course you'll never know
but but uh I think you'd you probably
You' be in the game of of of a game
practically how I spend most of my um um
day job is inferring to what extent is
this artifact or this person um doing
good um planning as inference good
planning um you know for example if
somebody's in a or in or asleep or has a
psychiatric disorder um you know you you
need to know to what extent they are um
and in what way they are self-modeling
um so you know um this is a slightly
sort of clinical and Abstract example
but illustrates a point that you will
never know whether something has free
will all you can do is infer that they
are behaving as if they had a generative
model that entailed a self model and and
thereby a model of the consequences of
action and therefore as if they were a
true agent and possibly they may know
they're a true agent they may not you
know they may be again um you know that
would require another level of of the
Markoff blanket is that what you had in
mind yes I mean I think um I guess the
the the kind of Hardline determinist
response would always be pushing you to
say whether that organism or particle
could have done
otherwise so it may have this reflexive
quality of okay I'm doing basing model
selection to my sense of self and we
will come to Consciousness because I
think that's the kind of Crux of this
issue is why is any of this happening
online anyway but it it might have this
self um reflexive notion of being a free
agent but the Hardline determinist from
the kind of external position of physics
might always say well could that bundle
of atoms ever have done otherwise in
terms of its basy and model selection
but it's it's again it might just be one
of
these sort of Loops that just keep
spinning um yeah it it's it's all um
fascinating I had a question that I've
just popped out of my head when I was
talking about Free Will which was
um I will come back to it I it will come
back to me um
Consciousness I know it's I don't know
if it's being considered I don't know if
we can call it a red herring yet in um
the academic world because it's become a
very hot topic um and people are getting
very heated about it and there's no need
to bring up particular examples of when
people have got heated about it but
people are very invested in their
theories and I guess rightly so it it
seems to be this
one thing that people can't
seem to couch within their theories of
everything if they have one do you let's
starting with very simple question do
you consider it to be a real problem do
you take something like the hard problem
seriously or for you is it more of a
meta question or can it or does a
deflationary account just do the job in
terms of the hard
problem um it really depends who I'm
talking to as my friend Jeff Beck would
say it depends which pants I'm wearing
so I think I think very much it's it's a
question of um a conversation and you
have to you have to infer how much
investment the person you're talking
about has in this issue and what
position they're taking um and I mean
that you know just in terms of being
polite and engaging you know with
Integrity in scientific uh debate or
indeed philosophical debate but I also
mean it uh in a slightly more
fundamental way that Consciousness is is
an illusion um and but I think Illusions
are fantastic they're literally
fantasies and I think that's what makes
our brains fantastic organs I think
they're hypotheses I think that the the
illusion is um the thing that we uh we
test it is the thing that generates the
predictions in predicted processing so I
think Consciousness is another illusion
um very much along the lines that one
reading of Andy Clark's basing qualia
paper um um that even qualitative
experience quaia are just Illusions
they're just things they're just
constructs we bring to the table
including selfhood um they're just
hypothesis illusions that are
particularly apt at um explaining
everything that we sense and making good
sense of it as as a a parsimonious H
hypothesis Consciousness itself I think
is ex exactly that because it only
applies the hypothesis is that um is
this thing conscious or not only applies
because there are other things in my
universe that I'm trying have to model
like you so it's the question is not
whether I am conscious the question is
whether you are conscious and of course
we've already said that is unanswerable
because you have a markof blanket so
it's an unanswerable question but
crucially it's a question about the
things are observe that I'm trying to
make sense of um it only becomes I think
um only in in the spirit of the metah
hard problem or The Meta problem um it
only becomes um um vexed when you make
the mistake of asking am I conscious I
don't think that's what the question is
there that's the illusion is not for me
it's for you uh the illusion is the
Consciousness is a construct a
hypothesis and a very plausible and all
the evidence that I have at hand would
suggest that you are conscious and
indeed literally because there is that
evidence um it is there in the sense of
an Evidence maximizing illusion
hypothesis or component of my generative
model um so I I go through that just to
make it clear that that you the answer
depends upon who you're talking to but
also who you are trying to um ascribe
Consciousness to so if I was talking to
um um
well if I was talking to um people like
yakob ho um um you the first thing he'd
say is that the free energy principle is
not a theory of Consciousness and in
fact he likes saying that every every at
every opportunity so so there's nothing
there's nothing
um there's nothing in the free energy
principle that has anything explicit to
say about explicit to say about
Consciousness on the other hand people
have used it in different ways to uh
address the hard problem um uh you could
take the view that Andy Clark takes that
there isn't a hard problem and perhaps
even with David charm's work recently on
The Meta problem The Meta hard problem
that's probably a more interesting
problem um or you could you could grasp
the the nettle and start to talk about
it if you were talking to um my
colleagues Chris F and and um um and um
Adam saffron and Maxwell ramstead and
and listen but um certainly um so I
think inspired uh by something that you
mentioned earlier on which was the
holographic principle in um um in in
Quantum information Theory where the
holographic screen now um plays the role
of of the Markoff blanket that separates
the inside and the outside in terms of
bulk reading and writing to um the um
the the
um the holographic screen um if you're
talking to him um then he would start to
talk about these minimal screens uh
these minimal Markoff blankets um and
develop quite a quite a sort of nice
argument that if you can't reduce in the
sense that we're talking about nested
Mark of blankets inside a markof blanket
if there are no more reductions at hand
then the only way that the internal
states of that irreducible Markoff
blanket can know about their own existen
is by acting upon lower levels and
therefore there's some um there's
something unique there there exists a
unique Mark of blanket that that that
you um maybe um uh have the attribute of
of Consciousness um if you're talking to
somebody like van Vice um um he would
you know tackle this in terms of um
trying to resolve uh a dualistic
position by offering a dual aspect
monism um of A maravian Sort and that
rests very heavily upon this information
geometry so if you remember before we're
talking about sort of a state space
equipped with free energy functionals um
on it um um that um plays the RO of a
cisal manifold but but there are two
cisal manifolds that are jointly sit sit
in this in the same state space of say
neural Activity one is that for any
given uh point there is a probability of
being there from a point of view of
neuronal activity and the thermodynamics
so this would be a
thermodynamic um kind of information
geometry and then the other one is what
the free energy principle uses which is
the encode using that point to encode
beliefs about external States so you got
two um information geometries belief
structures if you like um that supervene
on exactly the same um material um
process one of which is pertains to
probability distributions or beliefs
about the internal States and the other
one is probability distributions or
beliefs encoded by the internal States
about the external States so you could
construe one as being the mental and one
as being the material and then you've
got this dual aspect monism where you're
now asking questions about well what are
the lawful relationships between the
thermodynamic free energy and the um the
um the variational free energy that
pertains to beliefs about things so
you've got now a mechanics that talks
about beliefs and that may well be one
way of repairing that sort of a
dualistic approach um there's another
another perspective which you would get
if you were talking talking to talking
uh to people like um Julio tanon and um
SEL um well my colleagues involved in a
one of the Templeton Foundation absera
research uh um
collaborations um where you're trying to
find Bright lines between the free
energy principle and integr information
Theory um
um which is not necessarily the best
thing to do because a lot of integrated
information theory is exactly consilient
with the free energy principle however
if you are going to get
funding uh by uh trying to tease them
apart then the thing that distinguishes
those approaches to um uh Consciousness
is really the the active part that we
were talking about so uh boiling this
down in a way that some like I repeat
yakob Hoy might might articulate this is
It's the difference between seeing and
looking you know to be conscious I have
to look it's not enough to see um it's
um you know to be conscious I have to
listen it's not enough to hear uh so
you're putting action into games there
active sensing this this sort of closing
the the loop between the inside and the
outside may be um the thing that um is
necessary for Consciousness and simply
because you're saying that Consciousness
is an attribute of agents and agents
have to act what do they act on their
Sensations what does that mean they they
do active sensing so to be an agent is
to be an active sensor yes active
inference um and you if you're saying
that things that aren't agents can be
conscious then you wouldn't worry about
that but if you are committed to a deep
um to the notion that to be conscious um
of to have a minimal selfhood um then
you have to have the notion of self if
you have to have the notion of self then
you have to be an agent if you have to
be an agent you have to um um have
generative models about the consequences
of your agency your actions uh and that
has to have the temp then we go through
all of those nice links that we were
talking about before with temporality
and and you know and the like and indeed
the hierarch structure takes us back to
the Chris Fields um irreducible um uh
holographic screen or or um or Markoff
blanket so that would be the way that I
would um converse with that crowd uh
uh I run out yes I run out of people
that I might talk about it so I have to
find out what you like and then i' I'd
tell a story that that you like or let
you tell a story that uh that you like
well I guess my question to you would be
can you imagine a world of self
evidencing can you imagine okay let's
put it another way can you imagine a
perfect replica world like ours where
the lights are turned off entirely there
is no consciousness or is it do you
imagine it's a
necessary uh consequence of the way that
creatures are like like us are
structured that to do deep temporal
planning to do planning as inference
what whatever it is or self hooding we
need
Consciousness could there have been
another way that the Universe would have
unfolded without us being
online um I suspect not um sorry I I'm
torn between um um been taken by you
down sort of your philosophical zombie
uh routes versus um another um story
that comes out of the free energy
principle about Consciousness which is
um the um the the the importance of
self- modeling in relation to other
modeling and the fact that we are
actually living in a world um of things
like us so and one story I didn't cover
which is a story you would tell tell if
you were talking to um my friend Chris
fth or people who are much more
interested in the sort of social
neuroscience and uh or say attachment
Theory um and you know developmental
issues um that are induced by a sort of
evolutionary psychology view or Niche
construction for example all of these
views of Consciousness means that
Consciousness is just there um which is
where I started to infer um the state
the disposition the intentions State of
Mind of somebody else um why and how can
you do that well you can only do that if
that thing is sufficiently like you to
to be able to use your generative model
um as OB say your physical actions as a
model of their physical actions to infer
their intentions and the like um and
when one takes that to its limit then um
often what the real problem is is not in
terms of inferring the content of some
communication or some uh exchange of of
um semiotic cues it really is inference
about agency again it's did you do that
or did I do that so that ambiguity now
requires you to have a model of self
versus other so it's a much more
relational um um notion of self so you
know sometimes I think people talk about
minimal selfhood um as something which
is monolithic I don't think that's
necessary as part of a gen model it
certainly would be important to have um
different um different kinds of self you
know am I embarrassed am I in love you
know as we were talking about in you
know in the um tmbb meeting a few days
ago that would be you expressive and
very necessary part of generative model
where I have to contextualize my own
emotional and pro-social and autonomic
and moic behaviors um but there's no one
self it's a self you know self like this
like this and like this a more
fundamental relationship relational
aspect of selfhood is in relation to
otherhood you know mother uh you know
versus me and am I mom or
is is is mom a thing am I a thing I'm
the same thing as Mom you going to S
clan um uh sort
of arguments there so put simply what
that means is it may well be only in
universes or worlds that are populated
by ensembles of conspecifics that are
sufficiently similar would you need to
self Ood simply to distinguish self from
other in a universe where there's only
me I wouldn't need
selfhood so it would not be it would not
pay its way in terms of model complexity
or model evidence to have the notion of
me being a self if there's only me it
only pays its way if I now have to
entertain the hypothesis that either I
cause that or you cause that so the
question now is is it inevitable that
you get
a universe with lots of similar things
emerging all disambiguating themselves
or attributing agency to themselves in
the gold uh in the goldilock zone I
think it probably is I think that would
be I think if you
simulated sufficiently accurately
artificial life I think you would you
would get the emergence of um
populations of similar things and they
would Niche construct um and they would
be thereby Drive their own um sort of
Nest increasingly nested and um
structurally complicated um or at least
sparsely um structured um uh
organizations in terms of their Markoff
blankets um and that this would um this
at some point would inevitably invoke um
modeling of others and therefore almost
by default
a a a a a minimal notion of of of
selfhood I think that would be emergent
you but it would require being in the
Goldilocks regime for a sufficient
amount of time for this kind of Niche
construction uh cultural Niche
construction to actually play out so you
know you'd have to have this very slow
time scale providing the right kind of
context for this this kind of thing to
uh thing to emerge
yeah yeah I think my well I have some I
think I have some sympathies to the to
the argument that Charmers would have
laid out in or did lay out in
95 in his original hard problem paper
which is that I think I can still ask
the further question which is can
systems like me make the functional
distinction between myself and others
without there being a sense of what it's
like to be me can that just be an offlin
which is done purely in some algor
rhythmic manner which need not involve
some qualia of my
selfness so yeah there there's a point
that there's an element in me where I
don't want to say that that in a sense
resolves a hard problem because at least
I can hypothetically
Envision that being done
offline um I wonder whether you've given
much thought to Mark SS's idea which is
that Consciousness might be rooted in
affect
because this seems to me to be a bit
more of a self-confirming idea which is
that feelings must be felt now I think
there's still an open question there
which
is affect arises at the point of
uncertainty uh and drives us to resolve
uncertainty and when we do so we feel
good about ourselves now again I still
think when I was reading his book I
still had this open question why would
that have to why would why would affect
even emerge in that place why wouldn't
we just have this drive to resolve that
uncertainty without there being the
onliners so at least for me although I
may be wrong and I'm very happy to be
wrong there is still no simple
parsimonious explanation which can get
around this um this point that Charmers
makes which is you can give me the
function but you still you can't give me
the explanation power why it needs to be
online um and I wonder if there ever
will be some mechanism which is
sufficiently which isn't just purely
tautological or invokes consciousness as
some fundamental reality which makes me
which makes me wonder whether you've
heard of Donald Hoffman whether you're
familiar with his
work yes because I sense that in some
ways it has some
interesting implications maybe for the
free energy principle in the sense of
space and time not being fundamental
units of
reality we've been speaking a little bit
about how um where do space and time
come from how much do space and time
overlap in the sense of
generating um like we need expans
expansive creatures like us with
embedded Markoff blankets inevitably
have a sense of temporal modeling and
there's these interesting interactions
does the idea of space and time
being what he would say applications on
a desktop does that have any real do you
sense has any real ontological
implications for fre energy principle or
is it a red
herring um well you you've introduced
two important things I forgot to mention
Mark SS there another friend so to Mark
SS I would say it's all about this
irreducible Markoff blanket that acts
upon the rest of the brain where is that
action it's going to be in the neurom
modulat systems set the Precision the
Precision is exactly that fisher metric
which tells you about how much you're
updating your beliefs it is the way that
you do mental action it is as you
intimated um feeling in the sense that
it is quintessentially balanced by
increasing or decreasing the Precision
or uncertainty so um you know that's how
I would tie in Mark's um formulation to
which I think is internally consistent
with um say Chris Field's formulation or
um Van's formulation so Mark SS focuses
you know on those I think a key aspect
of um of active inference which is uh if
you're a psychologist it would be
attention it's basically acting in a way
on the inside to um get the an estimate
and deploy the right confidence or the
right Precision in um um mathematically
the curvature the of of of the um the
free energy in and of itself um getting
that right um and um you know that has a
lovely you know connection to attention
means that you can't divorce um
Consciousness from attention you can't
divorce it from agency in the sense of
mental action or internal action you now
have a deep connection to um Thomas
metzinger's um distinction between you
know um opaque and phenomenal
transparency um and uh and the way that
Mark would tell the story would be that
this is just feeling and feeling is at
the heart of of any qualitative
experience um so you yeah thank you for
the for reminding me he was one person I
forgot to to cover um the uh the second
thing um you know the the space and time
being Illusions um I mean yeah I sort of
start off there so I'm not quite sure
that it uh so if you're saying that
Donald's um and I should say he's a
friend I think I've never met him but I
think he's a friend of chrisfield and
Mike Levin so you know there's a a small
world here um but if if you're just
saying that um space and time are um
Illusions in the sense that we were
talking about Illusions as being
fantastic and the thing that makes us
into fantastic little beings and have
beings and um uh and our brain into a
fantastic organ yeah absolutely I mean
you know the question for me is why on
Earth would you um what what what must
be the case for us to have this illusion
of SpaceTime and that we are living in a
metric space and it's practically very
important I mean a lot of people spend a
lot of time in machine learning
embedding things in metric spaces um and
sometimes it's very difficult to see
what licenses then to do that uh you can
certainly see how it would work in terms
of projective geometries in metric
spaces um but the Deep question is why
you know you know I can't um I can't
imagine a um you know an amoeba really
having having a notion of of uh space um
I may be wrong um and so knows um um you
know if you listen to people like um um
Steven walram um you know the notion of
SpaceTime um itself May the illusion of
SpaceTime itself may be just an artifact
the fact that our sensory organs respond
very very slowly in relation to the
speed of light so if light traveled very
very slowly or imagine a world in which
um um we saw with sound and sound was
very very very slow um would that would
that be would that give you the illusion
of space um you and distance at an
action of the kind that you we sort of
implicitly assume when we're talking
about sort of visual objects so I think
he has this nice notion that you know in
this kind of World um with these kinds
of sense organs um you know when
something moves from here to here is it
the same thing anymore because that's
what you're saying when you have a
metric space in which objects move um
you know some certain symmetries or
invariances are inherit from the notion
of movement in a metric space but that
may well just be be be be a fantasy we
got gone off qualitative experience in
the hard problem yeah well no I by it
all it all ties back it's a Beau it's
it's it's a very good question which is
why would this why would space and time
be a an the interface for us I guess
that is the Deep question
um and yet it appears that that at least
it it it is something at least in
conscious awareness I did remember my
question and it actually feeds into the
last couple of questions I will have
which is you mentioned um that you spend
a lot of your time inferring in the
technical and Layman sense whether other
people have I think you say good
generative
models there's an interesting question
here I think which which I may have had
intuitively when I started reading about
active inference which is is there any
such thing as good self- evidencing in
the sense that I may so so a lot of as
of course you know as you wrote a lot of
the papers a lot of psychiatric
disorders and psychological disorders
have been rooted in um disruptions to
Precision waiting mechanisms for
example can we consider are the words
good bad optimal suboptimal are the
these useful terms in this context or is
it that that individual has a set of
priors which are different from you and
I and everyone else and we all actually
have a sense of we all have kind of
different prior so all self- evidencing
in unique ways and yet philosophical
vagueness allows us to Clump us together
into a group is there such a thing as
what it is to be a good self-evidence as
a human with beyond beyond just a
trivial point that we're not just
dissipating into the the Heat
right yeah that's an excellent question
um so I I think the answer to that is
yes um but as you correctly um pointed
out it should be qualified by the um the
complete class theorem So you you're
clearly referring to the complete
classroom so it might be just wise to um
just Define what that means and the
implications for discussions of good and
bad um um generative models um so the
complete class serum way i' like to
summarize it is that for any given pair
of behaviors and loss functions there
exists some prior that render your
behavior Baye optimal which means that
there is always a description of every
Behavior as base optimal under some
prize so in that sense you can't be good
or bad um where the thing is basically
your decisions because this inherits on
based in decision Theory so it's it's
not quite as full
uh active inference in accommodating um
information game but um within the
within the um confines of phasing
decision Theory you can't be um you
can't be good or bad you just have
different priers so you my favorite
example is that you know if we all went
to live on um on mars or a much heavier
planet people with Parkinson's disease
will probably be much better have better
prize you subpersonal prize in terms of
that don't be deficits because yeah they
move more slowly and sort of more
cautiously so yeah I think from the
point of view the complete class I think
it's important to bear that in mind you
know there are just different prize but
I I do think though you can sort of just
say well hang on a second what about
whether a good and bad prize and I think
then we get into this again this
hierarchical story because of course as
soon as you have a hierarch generative
model there are no prize you
everything's an empirical Prime
everything can be cont realize
everything is conditioned upon
everything else including your prize and
then you're just back into the um into
the game of self- evidencing what is
good self- evidencing it's achieving a
higher marginal likelihood or model
evidence um how would you do that by
finding the right prize how would you do
that by learning how would you do that
by changing your model basic model
selection or structure learning um how
would you do that in evolutionary scale
you do basic model selection with
natural selection so yeah um on that
view the log evidence as bounded by the
free energy um is just adaptive Fitness
is how well your prize are adaptive to
this world you are trying to explain so
I think yes absolutely you can you can
you can be a good self- evidenc you can
be a bad self- evidenc if you're a
natural selection um that matters
because if you're a bad self- evidenc
that means you won't be around um in the
um in the Next Generation so the
marginal likelihood of you existing at
an even ution time scale is low so the
your your evidence is also the
probability that you will be found exist
you you will exist so it's quite
important
to get to be a good self- evidenc sir
and because that's your marginal
likelihood of existing uh and I've now
slipped in another syn synonym for um
free energy Beyond um prediction
weighted prediction errors or Beyond on
surprise or surprise or
self-information Beyond log evidence uh
it's also statistics called The Log
marginal likelihood it's the the
likelihood of your sensory exchanges
with your world your econiche
having marginalized out or averaged away
all the unknowns which in this context
are all the states out there you know
the hidden causes or the sorry the
external states which you model in terms
of hidden uh in terms of hidden causes
um so yeah I think it's very important
to be good and bad at evidencing the
measure of goodness of Badness is just
the marginal likelihood of the modal
evidence and the free energy there is
nothing else um uh if you're saying does
that speak to some creatures that will
be able to actually assess how good they
are self- evidencing then the argument
say absolutely um people like mattius
jofy um looked at this specifically from
the point of view of emotion and
developed a whole taxonomy of emotion in
terms of um rates of change of free
energy and you get into stories of slope
chasing uh um looking for gradients and
gradients and gradients of uh self-
evidencing on the measurement of the
goodness of self- evidencing which is uh
which is which is the free energy um
more refined stories more recent stories
um would basically be looking at certain
kinds of
uncertainty um being encoded explicitly
in your generative model as underlying
affect uh particularly the the your
certainty about what you're going to do
next for example then we get back to um
the story that Mark SS would like to
tell which is um the Precision of your
beliefs is the most you know the most
important attribute that defines um you
know its veillance and that your your
feeling at this sort of minimal
effective level yeah yeah the complete
class firm is an interesting one because
I think it leads people it leads one
into a potent these potential strange
conclusions um it makes me think of
animals that commit suicide oddly so um
I think sort of AIDS might explode
themselves in the context of a
predator It ultimately comes back down
to your model evidence I guess so I am
the type of creature that will commit
suicide if I'm in the presence of a of a
ladybug of course but then those kinds
of examples I sense for me show that the
words good or bad I'm just pushing a
little bit back just intuitively the
words good or back in in in in the form
of uh continued existence slightly put
the cart before the horse because who
said that that's the imperative so if I
existed in the world where my everyone's
imperative was to no longer exist you
know know God
forbid then that then I would be doing
bad self- evidencing on that standard if
I didn't if I continued to persist so is
there a point at which even the yeah
like do you see how well do you see that
argument holding any water um or is it
just now we're just s dissolving into
semantics well no no I think I think
it's an interesting thing to to
contemplate uh you you you you're you're
basically I think undermining um that
particular argument by uh um proof
abductory absurdum um so if you think
you are the kind of thing that will uh
self-destruct or aviate or commit
suicide um then uh you can't exist
because you killed yourself
right yeah so I will be extremely
surprised um if there were any um uh
common natural um um subhuman artifacts
that kill themselves I didn't know about
the aphid example very I mean obviously
Lemmings is is the sort of popular
culture one but um um you I think
they'll be extremely rare and you and
then you have to understand the um
selection at an evolutionary or
transgenerational level um um in order
to apply the free energy principle um
but in you know I think you're
absolutely right
I'm very mindful that a couple of weeks
ago I was asked to review a paper
applying Act of inference to suicide and
it was a very Artful paper um and uh I
do remember thinking I'm not sure
whether the point was made implicitly or
explicitly in the paper but you know
it's it made me think in exactly the way
that you were you were um talking about
um you know the imperatives to survive
and and are they the right way to think
about the causes of our behavior um I I
would say absolutely not not this is not
about um wanting to survive this is
simply wanting to avoid uncharacteristic
Sensations and then we put a post talk
hypothesis oh that's because I want to
survive then right but that's a fantasy
that's another illusion uh so you know
we do not know what it is like to be
dead so yes it cannot be well it can be
surprising but it certainly can't be the
kind of surprise that you'd register in
terms of a free energy so it's not that
we're frightened of being dead we're
frightened um we are going to avoid bya
these pragmatic constraints um states
that we've have inherited that um for
portend um cessation and dissipation and
death death in in all itself is not at
all frightening we go to sleep every
every um suspension of got to go to
sleep every every night um so you know I
I I would I would um sorry yeah and the
final point I think is I think what you
were doing though you were probably um
creating a slightly vexed and
self-defeating argument by saying uh by
assuming that um we can understand
things in terms of imperatives the whole
point of the free enery principle is
that there aren't any imperatives this
is where it starts as things that exist
must behave like this and part of the
behaving like this means that you can
interpret them as optimizing something
and complying with imperatives but
that's just an interpretation that
you'll bring to the table when you apply
it to something else if you then apply
it to yourself then you know then things
might get interesting you might have
hard problems but there are no
imperatives you know in fact even
minimizing free energy is not an
imperative you can have the free energy
principle applying to um things that
have very dissip uh dissipated
attracting sets um that have very very
um High entropy um all it's saying is
that there has to be a certain uh
gradient flow that count as the random
fluctuations then you ask yourself well
hang on a second so why does it look as
if we're always trying to attain some
very precise
homeostasis um and the free enery
principal would turn that on its head it
would say well look okay in some
universes there may be very precise
things um and these precise things what
would they look like oh it would look as
if they were trying that they had um
aspirations to EV evincing a very
precise homeostasis and indeed
allostasis so you get this notion of
another kind of natural thing which are
precise things um so if precise things
exist it would look as if they um they
are um compelled to comply to very
specific
imperatives but from The View it's not
saying they exist because they comply
with the imperative it's saying
existence implies it looks as if they
have this imperative right now one final
point you know I'm I'm aware that we'
we've now approaching three
hours well final point though I you
introduced the word optimization I think
that was
um the right a right and important um um
thing to introduce because you know it's
only when you bring free energy into the
game as a bound on marginal likelihood
or self the negative lock marginal
self-information or surprise or
surprisal do you convert an existential
description into an optimization problem
so that's exactly the move that Richard
fan made when he introduced variation
free energy he had this impossible
marginalization problem that to actually
evaluate the marginal likelihood of
paths so exactly the same kind of
problem that we're talking about in
terms of uh what my prior over policies
and plans and paths into the future um
you can't you can't evaluate that
exhaustively it's analytically and
practically physically not realizable so
the marginalization problem the true
inference problem if you like uh the
true existential uh problem if there is
one um cannot be solved but what you can
do is introduce this and turn it into an
optimization problem so just by using
free energy um or just by appealing to
this Tey that comes from um predicate
everything on this evidence lower bound
you are actually saying that it looks as
if creatures that exist are optimizing
something what does it look what are
they optimizing it looks as if they're
optimizing a bound on their um marginal
likelihood or their adaptive Fitness um
what does that look like well it looks
exactly like basing inference uh or if
you're talking to somebody machine
learning it would look as if you're um
optimizing your negative variation for
Energy is known as an elbow so this is a
evidence lower bound it is exactly
objective function used in um sort of
high-end neural networks like variation
Auto encoders um so you know I think
that the distinction between um just
being and optimizing is quite crucial
and you're absolutely right that once
you make the move um of um framing
things in terms of variational bounds
using variational calculus or
variational Bays um then you have
actually committed to an optimization
narrative but you didn't have to just to
exist you you you could uh yes yeah yeah
I I was gonna have this funky
philosophical argument about needing to
exist to predict but I won't go there I
won't go there um because we are going
to wrap
up all of this philosophical
mathematical thoughts has and
Consciousness thoughts has brought to my
mind Thomas Nagel um Thomas Nagel has
this idea that death is bad because life
is inherently
good and we've been talking about life
and being and what it is to be and what
one needs to do to be and persist to be
if we're going to wrap everything up
is there a sense in which that kind of
related to what we were just talking
about in terms of imperatives of course
there is no imperative to be in any
sense but you said it was an interesting
thing you said there was it looks like
we are all
being anyway right even if we didn't
have to it looks like we are there's no
God granted plan for us to be but we
seem to be doing it anyway does any of
nagle's romantic philosophical idea that
life is fundamentally good being is good
does any of that resonate with
you um yes it does because it's it's
it's you know it's nice isn't it and I
you'd
probably you you'd probably sort of
license that with with um phrases of the
kind that you know to exist is to be
curious um so this speaks to this sort
of um you know the ability to respond to
um epistemic affordances and certainly
you know to exist as curious creatures
um is obviously the good way to exist in
you in any given world and it's you and
would be mandated um I can't resist
saying though of course this only really
applies to you it doesn't apply to me so
so you are good because you are curious
and you
exist and I wish I could say the same
for me but I can't strictly speaking but
you could if you wanted to I could I
could abstract to you in some degree I
could infer that there is a you great um
and then I guess we can wrap it up there
with one more question we've just spoken
about life being
good I'll flip the question I don't
think I've ever heard you talk about
death although we briefly touched upon
it um I won't make it too personal
but if life is kind of good in some
sense because of the concomitant parts
of living as we do as I don't know if
it's good to be a stone but it's nice to
be me having these
conversations would that make death bad
is that is there is there a is you said
we fear dying because we
fear in an affective sense um that which
we don't expect to the states we don't
expect to embody and in some sense we
don't expect to embody death because it
doesn't fit in with our priors but
beyond that free energy principle
perspective is there a broader position
in which just returning back to the
fabric of the universe is bad is there
something to say about re-entering that
Mark of blanket does do my markof
blankets dissipate um what what does
that process look like and and does that
strike fear in you or strike
awe um well more or but I don't want to
overstate it
um it is it is beautiful um from a from
a p mathematical point of view um so I I
have a very sanguin view of this and
we've already said you know you've never
been dead I've never been dead so no one
can tell me it's an unpleasant
experience um so I I'm not particularly
I I I'm not going to um avoid being dead
I certainly think all the all the paths
to being dead Pro probably very
surprising and unpleasant so I'm going
to avoid
those death in and of itself I don't
think is uh is sort of um
quintessentially bad um in the same way
that um Nal being curious and being
engaged with the world is a good is it
is good while you exist um um um I think
that's perfectly okay but I think death
is um or the life cycle let's call it a
life cycle that it's slightly less um um
imbued with um morbidity um the life
cycle is is is quite important because
um if you just look at um if you just
take this um
multiscale um um view of um
self-organization cast in terms of this
basic mechanics um that you know for
example natural selection being based in
model selection um then um if you put
that together with what we're talking
about before about
um ecosystems and Niche
construction constantly changing the
lived
world then what you need to do is to do
constant Basin model selection um in
order to get the right structures very
much in the spirit that we talking about
before where there are good priers and
there are bad priers in the sense of the
marginal likelihood or adaptive
Fitness to learn earn those good prize
you sometimes have to start from scratch
again um with a different structure and
of course this is exactly what pay in
model selection does via structure
learning at an evolutionary time scale
will entail death so that picture
basically says that we have to keep
refreshing soort of sometimes cast in
terms of Bas opal forgetting so we the
fact that we die are Bas is is could be
construed as a base optimal forgetting
where we are the environment's memory of
what is good for this Eco dis but the
environment or least natural selection
knows that the environment is changing
so what was good last generation will
not necessarily be good for the
subsequent generation so it has to
forget in the same way that you learn by
forgetting you have insights by
dispensing with redundant information so
in a sense death for in that life cycle
is an essential part of um uh of the
self- evidencing of the species so it
may be bad for you I suppose you know in
a nesque sense in that it's denying the
opportunity to be curious and engaged
with the lived world but it's certainly
good for your children and your
children's children right right right
I'm a I'm a for warning for them that's
good I'm glad to I'm glad to be that
porn in that game and a kind of cheery
note on which to end um will be a
slightly morbid question Carl this was
an absolute pleasure um despite the
occasional Wi-Fi hiccup I think it's um
it's gone you know I've been I'm
incredibly happy with it thank you so
much for being our first guest um and
answering my sweet of sometimes bizarre
questions it was a real Joy on my part
right well it was been a real pleasure
talking to you your questions were
excellent I have no idea how long you're
going to have to spend editing all this
I I thank you again for that opportunity
to uh you know to talk about these
wonderful issues and hopefully we'll do
it again excellent thank you go